I have a worldview in which I don't think DeFi protocols should change.
I think DeFi protocols themselves should be as open and composable and permissionless as possible.
I think certain assets, certain tokens, should be permissioned.
And I think when you combine completely open, completely composable,
DeFi protocols and assets, some of which might have to be KYC and some of which are completely
permissionless, you get the best possible end state.
Here we are with Robert Leschner, who needs no introduction to our audience,
but still co-founder of Superstate and Compound.
Robert, it's so great to finally have you on the Define podcast.
Kami, thanks for having me on.
So Robert was one of the, I think probably the first DeFi founder interview I ever did
when I was at Bloomberg back in 2018 and had just like very little idea of what DeFi was.
I think like anyone, I don't think anyone had an idea of what DeFi was at the time.
I still don't know what DeFi is to be honest.
Yes, good answer.
Okay, so obviously from Compound, now you are at Superstate.
You pioneered a decentralized ending with Compound and now you are doing something very
good friend, tokenizing real world assets with Superstate.
I love kind of your, what was the thought line between those two and wondering your view of
on chain slash DeFi finance has changed.
So here's the thought line.
When I first founded Compound, starting in 2017, I predicted somewhat incorrectly that all assets
would wind up being tokens and blockchains.
And when we launched Compound in 2018, when it was during 2019, 2020, 2021, 22, 23,
all of the assets that you could use in Compound and any DeFi protocol, for that matter,
were really crypto native assets.
Tokens, oftentimes of other crypto projects that were issued on a blockchain for the first time,
they weren't coming from, you know, an off-chain system.
They were basically being issued on chain.
And this was amazing because this allowed people to prove out the functionality of DeFi
protocols and autonomous pieces of software that could create new products and marketplaces.
And I always thought that, you know, that would change, right?
I knew that was going to be the case when we first launched Compound.
You know, I just assumed, though, at a certain point, you know, the tokens that you use on chain
and DeFi protocols would start to be stocks and bonds and real estate and commodities and
all these other things as opposed to just the tokens of other crypto projects.
And the whole thing, for me, felt very self-referential and that the ceiling for how
big things could get was really limited until, as a society, we could start to bring in all
of the assets and value that didn't live on a blockchain yet.
And to have not trip their native tokens be the primary assets within DeFi protocols.
And so for me, that was like something that I couldn't stop thinking about.
And I said, okay, well, I want to figure out how to bring all of the stuff that's not yet
composable with DeFi on chains so that it can be composable with DeFi.
That means a lot of sense, for that to happen, probably the biggest roadblock has been a regulatory
one. How to do this in a compliant way and others tried to do that before and it didn't
turn out so well. So what's different now? And if you can kind of go through how you've solved
these problems? Well, there's actually a lot that's different now than, you know, eight years ago
or seven years ago, right? So people have been trying pretty much since as long as Ethereum has
existed to be tokenizing securities and tokenizing off chain assets. It hasn't really picked up
until the last year or so part of that's regulatory, but there's a lot of other factors going into
this. So here are the sort of core building blocks that I think are necessary to tokenize
off chain assets at scale, right? Yeah, obviously you can do one off experiments and over the years
we've always seen one off experiments that haven't really gotten any traction or critical mass,
but you know, I've been done, you know, to put a flag in red. So here's the core ingredients that
are necessary that have to come together. So the first are issuers, right? Whose assets
are coming on shape? In the past, there have been like a small number of people willing to like
tokenize their assets or wanting to put the number of issuers of assets has been pretty low. And that's
really started to change over the past two years, right? That's the first piece. The second piece
are the use cases, right? When I started in 2017, there was nothing that you could possibly do
with a tokenized asset once it was on chain, right? Besides hold it in your wallet, any asset
that's owned off chain, metaphorically speaking, already sits in someone's wallet, bringing it on
chain without DeFi protocols to use it in or new use cases doesn't really accomplish much. And so,
you know, the use cases are here, right? We've been proving out amazing DeFi use cases for
eight years now, okay? That's real. Then there's the demand. How many people want to hold a tokenized
security and all of the one-off experiments that happened over the last, you know, many years,
the number of people that wanted to own this stuff really small. We're just now getting to the point
where a lot of people want to own this stuff. And lastly is regulatory. And you mentioned this,
I also see this as like a hugely important, you know, ingredient, but it hasn't actually
changed that much. So in some ways, it's changed less than people think. Most of the assets that
people are tokenizing are securities. We've known their securities for a very long time, right?
At Superstate, we are tokenizing securities. We're not tokenizing commodities yet. We're
not tokenizing things that are not securities. We're tokenizing things that are very obviously
securities. There's nothing that we can do right now that we couldn't have done from a legal and
regulatory perspective a year ago, or even three years ago. What has changed dramatically is
everyone else's willingness around us to interact with these assets. Now that we're starting to see
incredible regulatory clarity. What I mean by this is like, you know, I could have launched a TVL fund
and tokenized it under Gary against four years ago. Would people want to interact with it, touch it,
add support for it, you know, would institutions want to use it? No, because even if it was legal,
they would have faced, you know, a lot of compliance costs, investigation costs,
they would have faced all sorts of additional costs and it would have been a burden. That's
what's different is that it's not a burden. So if you talk to any institution of Wall Street,
you're like, Hey, would you like to interact with tokenized securities? They're like,
actually, yes, like, we're incredibly excited about this. And you know, we're incredibly excited
by the tailwinds coming from the SEC and creating regulatory clarity. And so it's not that things
went from being illegal to legal, right, but what really swissed from a regulatory perspective was,
you know, an extremely cumbersome headwind to, you know, a tailwind of, call it even like,
soft support, right? There are no real new policies that, you know, flip a bullion from a zero to a
one here. You know, we just see a much more accommodative atmosphere. And this is a very
institutional market for institutions, knowing that they're not at odds with their regulators
everything. And so the regulatory stuff is an absolute game changer. And it has absolutely been
one of the things that started to create this catalyst for tokenized assets. But it's not that
this was like illegal a couple years ago, which just wasn't encouraged, was discouraged.
No, that's a great point. And so speaking of institutional demand, I think what I've seen,
at least, is from institutions, there's been a lot more appetite to issue assets on chain,
right? Like BlackRock with mid-middle, Franklin Templeton and so on, they're issuing their tokenized
money markets. But are you seeing demand from institutions to actually buy these tokens or
is demand really coming still from more crypto native players?
Yeah, it's a great question. Let me walk you through the products suite of what
we're tokenizing, because I can just see differences. So the first product that we launched was a
tokenized tea bill fund. The second product we launched was a tokenized basis yield fund.
And the third product that we're launching are tokenized equity. So all of these have like a
very different audience to them. In general, it's all crypto native. And why is it entirely
crypto native? It's because right now the people that want to hold a tokenized asset on a blockchain
are people that are using crypto wallets, crypto custodians, crypto realities in general.
We're not yet to the point where tokenized securities are the thing that happens under the hood for
traditional market participants. You know, eventually, trad five players will be using tokenized things
under the hood. And they won't say, I'm using crypto, they're just going to know that things
settle faster. They're more programmable. They're just more efficient and better. But right now,
we still learn a moment where all of the users are crypto first. On the table side, you know,
there's a lot of demand from, you know, stablecoin projects. There's a lot of demand from, you know,
applications that are looking for a risk free rate that they can embed underneath their product in a
composable and programmatic way, right? There are some crypto hedge funds, crypto venture funds
people that are saying, Oh, like, let me take, you know, stablecoins and have a productive
product of use for them and tokenized T bills that I can enter and exit quickly. You know,
but it's for the most part, people that are just looking for a very basic risk free rate that they
can enter and exit quickly. And that's honestly very composable. And so we see a lot of demand
from an application developer more than anything else. Our basis product, it's risky, right? It
goes up and it sometimes goes down a little bit, right? Because crypto markets are volatile.
So it's a high yield product with a little bit of risk there. And so it's not really suitable
as a building block in the same way for a stablecoin, let's say. And so the use case,
they're actually, you know, instead of being very application focused is significantly more
speculative focused. And so the users of it are oftentimes, you know, people that are
comfortable with risk. It's a lot of crypto native hedge funds. It's players that are actually
using this composable with d5. So it, you know, our, you know, basis fund is integrated into
Aave Horizon, which is an RWA market. You see a lot of people leveraging it up and actually
using it as a composable asset. It's a lot of sophisticated players. And so it skews much more
hedge fund than it does applications. Although, you know, we've recently announced like a couple
weeks ago that, you know, Spark, you know, the sky slash maker project was integrating USCC.
And so we do see some protocol adoption there, but it tends to be much more
crypto native speculative. And then lastly, our token is equities. And these are really
a nascent immersion product. We haven't yet turned on a lot of the use cases for
and users to be able to use them right now. We're really just in a testing phase.
And what's that mean? And who's using it? Well, right now what we're doing is, you know, we're
approaching tokenization of equities a little bit differently than other projects. You know,
we're not, you know, a startup that goes on and buys 100 different stocks and puts them in 100
different SPVs or holds them at a custodian or in a trust and issues tokens against them.
Our model of tokenization is actually quite different. We offer what we call native tokenization
or canonical tokenization. And so the way this works is we're basically the infrastructure for
a public company, someone that's trading on the NASDAQ or your stock exchange to tokenize their
own stock and where they're agent and issuance platform. And so when a company tokenizes their
own stock, it's their official stock. The same shares the trade on the NASDAQ or your stock
exchange is now a token on the blockchain. And what this means is that you can, you know,
through a relatively for now, clunky process, you can actually migrate shares between a brokerage
account and a token on the blockchain and back again. And so right now we're really testing.
We're testing moving shares from brokerage accounts to tokens, tokens to brokerage accounts
and making sure the sort of underlying infrastructure of equity tokenization works before activating
a lot of the DeFi use cases and really seeing for the first time, who are the users of the stock?
It's so interesting. I mean, all these use cases, but I'll ask you a follow up questions on specifically
tokenized stocks. We're seeing so many players focus on this use case. And yeah, they all have
kind of their different approaches. Yours is super interesting kind of to make the tokenized stocks
the actual equity of the company. But if this is the path forward, how do you see just the broader
tokenized equity market evolving? Do you see kind of a tokenized equities will be from just
new company's issuing stocks or wouldn't super say do you have a path forward later for existing
equities to also come on chain? Yeah, absolutely. So I want to preface by saying I think both overall
models of tokenization work and will exist. I think there's the super state model where it's like
the canonical stock. There's disadvantages of this model. It doesn't scale as effectively. We have to
work with issuers one by one to bring new tokenized equities to market. The other model, you know,
any startup like even to start at this like a day old can basically go and tokenize the top 100
stocks. They're making an entirely new asset when they do that. There's like weird credit risk
associated with the startup. There's differences in like what are the rights of the tokens,
not that the top, but it's extremely scalable. Any startup listening to this podcast could
probably go and make their own wrap stock relatively easily. Right. And so I think there's actually
a really interesting opportunity for both. I think institutions and the existing financial
market structure is going to strongly prefer the super state model, which is, hey, this is the
same stock with the same rights, the same governance, the same risks. It's not a different security.
And I think retail and I think international users are going to strongly prefer the second model.
Yeah, we don't care if it's a new asset. As long as it tracks the price with like 99% correlation
and has basically the same liquidity, what's it matter? Right. I think it's going to be much
more retail focus. And I think that's where it's going to see success. And so I think both models
are viable. I just think they have very different customers long term. And then, well, all of these
use cases and arguably market as a whole right now is still really small, right? It's I think
it's 300 million. Nothing. Yeah. It's like we haven't even started yet. Yeah. And you've mentioned
like right now, it's mostly crypto native. So what's it going to take? Like, what's where does the next
leap come from? How when do institutions actually start buying these talks? What use case you think
is going to be the thing that makes this a larger market? Yeah, it's a great question. I think it's
DeFi. I mean, frankly, most people, including most people around the world have the ability to buy
stocks right now. That doesn't really change with organization, frankly, right? It's us. I think it's
being able to do interesting things with these in DeFi protocols. That's going to be the tipping
point. When stablecoins came around and I was there with stablecoins really picked up in 2018,
very few people wanted stablecoins. It wasn't until it was like, wow, like you can use these in
every single type of DeFi protocol that you know, you really started to see explosive growth. And
yes, there's a lot of activity outside of DeFi protocols. But that was what like blew it up,
frankly, was like, okay, like you can trade on chain, you can borrow on chain. There's lots of
markets being created on centralized exchanges for these things. You know, oh, you can move it
between a DeFi protocol and a centralized exchange. It just became incredibly useful
with new reasons for them to exist. And so, you know, people have had dollars for hundreds of years,
stablecoins, literally better. I had tokenized equities and tokenized securities more broadly,
or got to go through the same thing until there was real use cases in DeFi and centralized exchanges,
the ability to move between the two very seamlessly. I don't think people are going to prefer the
crypto version of this. The Robinhoods of the world, as is the Vanguard, the Schwabs, whatever
brokerage account people use, they're pretty good today. They're not perfect. They're pretty good.
Right. And so, I think it takes like this step function of offering something new before people
will say like, oh, actually, I strongly prefer the crypto version. Like, you know,
there's reasons for this to migrate from my wallet into the crypto version.
I love that insight. But, you know, in that world, DeFi becomes something different, right? Like,
there's there would be a KYC aspect, it wouldn't be like truly permissionless. What do you think,
you know, there could be some kind of counterargument to this model where DeFi grows with the tokenization
of real world assets. And it just becomes gated and permissions. What do you say to that line of
criticism? I have a worldview in which I don't think DeFi protocols should change. I think DeFi
protocols themselves should be as open and composable and permissionless as possible. I think certain
assets, certain tokens should be permissioned. And I think when you combine completely open,
completely composable, you know, DeFi protocols and assets, some of which might have to be KYC
and some of which are completely permissionless, you get the best possible end state, which is,
yeah, some users won't be able to touch this token because of the geography they're in or
because they're not accredited or because X, Y, and Z. But a DeFi protocol will be able to bring
all of those under one breath and say, oh, we have permissionless assets. We have, you know,
geo-blocked assets. We have accredited blocked assets. We have all of it, but the DeFi protocol
can support it all, unified model. I think that's the future. And I think in that world, like,
yes, an individual shouldn't necessarily have access to every single asset if it
doesn't conform with the laws, you know, like, I don't believe in illegal assets. I believe in legal
assets and radically open infrastructure for them to run on. And I think you'll have the compounds
and obviously new swaps and curves and, you know, everything's of the world one day supporting
a mix of stuff. And that's good. What's your view on how just broader finance looks like
under this model? Like, do you think all assets come on chain and everyone is able to
transact in in DeFi freely? Where do you see this kind of convergence of two worlds going?
I mean, the people that are using DeFi protocols, the people that have their money on chain right now,
are crypto power users, right? It's, you know, in some cases, and we're starting to see this the
most with stablecoins, we're starting to see DeFi become like infrastructure for traditional
applications, right? We're starting to see a lot more fintechs trying to use DeFi under the hood.
And it's something that we've been predicting. I mean, like you and I and most of the people
listening to this program for years now, it's like, Oh, DeFi will be infrastructure. We're not
seeing this with most assets. We're not seeing this with most tokens. Most tokens are not being
used outside of like the crypto native on chain, mostly speculative stuff. But we're starting to
see like underlying infrastructure for mostly stablecoins. I think that's what happens next,
as we see, you know, DeFi become underlying infrastructure for equities. And for things that
there's a neat demand in traditional markets for it. And I think that's where it goes. And what
happens next is like we see DeFi plus tokenized securities eventually start to power all sorts of
stuff that the end users aren't even knowing that they're in right with Web. In this world,
which DeFi primitives or protocols when to be really simple about this, there's only really
three core primitives, okay, in general, like to this day, right? There's obviously a lot of
edge cases and new stuff and but you have decks, you have Baro land and you have Perbs. Those are
like the three crypto, most important primitives, right? Yes, there's a lot of other stuff. There's
a lot of other DeFi applications, but like those are the big three, you know, I think you're gonna
have tokenized assets playing a huge role in all three. And then finally, I'm very curious on your
the lessons that you took from compound and how you're applying that to super safe.
Yeah, I mean, there's a lot of lessons, I mean, like endless lessons. One of them is that, you know,
decentralized governance and development really slows things down. You know, we've seen this,
you know, sort of reality play out from so many different projects in crypto, you know, as they
shift from like a very centralized team to a decentralized team. And, you know, I don't think that,
you know, succeeded very well with a compound, frankly, you know, that shift from like, oh, one
team does it all to, Hey, the community can do it. Like that was a really like rough transition
that I think slowed things down tremendously. And so, you know, super state, you know, if we were
to have a token to be very far into the future, it would not be early on. And you know, the sort of
life cycle of things. Interesting. That hint at a token there. Oh, I'm not hinting at a tag. I'm
just saying like, I've gone through the shift from, you know, centralized to decentralized and like,
it's a headwit. Like it really is awesome. Robert, well, we'll have to do another one of these.
But amazing to have you on the show. Thanks so much. And yeah, super exciting to see what you're
doing with super state. Thank you.